Pirates.
They range from scary to hilarious.
Famous tales have been told for decades,
from real-life pirates like Blackbeard to
Captain Jack Sparrow
and the Pirates of the Caribbean.
This documentary dives into the facts and
history, including the golden age of
pirates, during the 17th
century, much of which took place in the
famous Caribbean islands.
In this edition of DOC TV's monster horror
documentary series, we'll look at pirates,
riches and
treasure hunting.
Ahoy mateys, let's get sailing Piracy
emerged from and reflected,
on a smaller scale, disputes over trade
and colonization among the competing
European powers of the era,
including the kingdoms of Spain, Britain,
the Netherlands, France and Portugal.
Most pirates in this period were of Welsh,
Dutch, English, French and Irish origin.
Numerous pirates came from impoverished
urban environments exploring ways to make
money and reprieve.
London in particular, was known for
increased unemployment, poverty and
crowding, which forced individuals to
piracy.
Piracy also delivered power and quick
riches.
Historians like John Fisk indicate the
start of the golden age of piracy at
around 1650,
when the end of the wars of religion
allowed European countries to continue the
expansion of their colonial
empires.
This involved significant seaborne trade.
and an overall economic improvement.
Money was to be made or stolen and much
trekked by ship.
French buccaneers established themselves
on northern Hispaniola as early as 1625,
but
lived mainly as hunters of pigs and cattle
rather than robbers.
Their shift to full-time piracy was
incremental and somewhat motivated by
Spanish measures to wipe out both
the buccaneers and the prey animals on
which they relied.
The buccaneers' migration from
Hispaniola's landmass to the more
defensible offshore island of Tortuga
restricted
their resources and accelerated their
piratical raids.
According to Alexander Exquemlin, a
buccaneer and historian who remains a
decisive source on this period,
the Tortuga buccaneer Pierre Le Grand
pioneered the settlers' attacks on
Galleons, making the return journey
to Spain.
The English capture of Jamaica from Spain
in 1655 boosted the growth of buccaneering
on
Tortuga.
The early English governors of Jamaica
voluntarily gave letters of marque to
Tortuga buccaneers and their fellow
citizens.
At the same time, the development of Port
Royal supplied these raiders with a far
more beneficial and gratifying place
to sell their booty.
In the 1660s, the new French governor of
Tortuga Bertrand d'Augeron also provided
privateering commissions to his colonists
and English cutthroats from Port Royal.
These circumstances brought Caribbean
buccaneering to its peak.
Several elements caused Anglo-American
pirates, some of whom had been introduced
to piracy during the buccaneering
period, to look beyond the Caribbean for
treasure as the 1690s began.
The end of Britain's Stuart years had
revived the traditional animosity between
France and Britain, terminating
the fruitful cooperation between English
Jamaica and French Tortuga.
The destruction of Port Royal by an
earthquake in 1692 further decreased the
Caribbean's
interests by destroying the pirates'
principal market for the stolen loot.
Caribbean colonial governments started to
dump the traditional policy of no peace
beyond the line.
under which it was comprehended that war
would continue and thus letters of marque
would be bestowed in the Caribbean
regardless of peace treaties signed in
Europe.
Subsequently, commissions would be
provided only in wartime and their
restrictions would be rigorously executed.
Also, much of the Spanish main had been
depleted.
Maracaibo alone had been plundered three
times between 1667 and 1670-80,
while Rio de la Hacha had been raided five
times and Tulu eight.
At the same time, England's less favoured
colonies, including New York, Bermuda and
Rhode Island,
had become cash-starved by the Navigation
Acts.
Vendors and governors enthusiastic for
cash were inclined to overlook and even
support pirate voyages.
One colonial administrator defended a
pirate because he thought it very harsh to
hang people that brings in
gold to these provinces.
Although some pirates working out of New
England and the middle colonies targeted
Spain's more remote Pacific coast
colonies well into the 1690s and beyond,
the Indian Ocean was a wealthier and more
attractive
target.
India's economic output dwarfed Europe's
during this time, especially in high-value
luxury products like
calico and silk, which made perfect pirate
booty.
At the same time, No effective navies
sailed the Indian Ocean, leaving both
local shipping and the
diverse East India Company's crafts
vulnerable to invasion.
This set the stage for the renowned
pirates of Thomas II, Robert Culliford,
Henry Every, and, although
his guilt stays contentious, William Kidd.
Peace treaties concluded the War of the
Spanish Succession in 1713 and
1714.
As a result, thousands of seamen,
including European privateers who had
served in the West Indies, were
rid of military commitment when the
cross-Atlantic colonial shipping trade
started to explode.
In addition, European seafarers who had
been driven by unemployment to work on
board merchantmen,
including slave vessels, were frequently
eager to leave that profession and turn to
pirating, giving pirate
captains a constant pool of draftees on
miscellaneous coasts across the Atlantic.
In 1715, pirates tackled a significant
attack on Spanish divers trying to
retrieve gold
from the Sumcombe treasure galleon Orca de
Lima near Florida.
The heart of the pirate squad was a group
of English ex-privateers, all of whom
would shortly be exalted in
infamy.
Henry Jennings, Benjamin Hornigold, Samuel
Bellamy of wider galley fame, Edward
England
and Charles Vane.
The raid was triumphant, but contrary to
their expectations, the governor of
Jamaica declined to permit
Jennings and his mates to spend their loot
on his island.
With Kingston and the declining Port Royal
sealed to them, Jennings, Hornigold, and
their mates based
themselves at Nassau, on the island of New
Providence in the Bahamas.
Nassau would become a base for these
pirates and their many draftees until the
arrival of Governor Woods Rogers in
1718, which signalled the cessation of the
Republic of Pirates.
Rogers and other British governors had the
power to absolve pirates under the King's
Act of Grace, while
Hornigold accepted this pardon to become a
pirate others.
like Blackbeard, returned to piracy
following their acquittal.
Transatlantic shipping traffic between the
Caribbean Africa and Europe started to
skyrocket in the 18th
century, a model known as the triangular
trade and became an affluent target for
piracy.
Trade ships voyages from Europe to the
African coast, trading fabricated goods
and weapons for enslaved
people.
The traders then journeyed to the
Caribbean to sell the slaves and return to
Europe with merchandise like sugar,
cocoa and tobacco.
In another triangular trade route, ships
would carry preserved cod, raw materials
and rum to Europe,
where a part of the shipment would be sold
for fabricated goods, which, along with
the rest of the initial shipment, were
then hauled to the Caribbean, where they
were traded for molasses and sugar, which
were then borne to New England.
Ships in the triangular trade frequently
made money at each location.
As a component of the settlement of the
War of the Spanish Succession, the British
South Sea Company received the
Haciento, a Spanish government agreement
to provide slaves to Spain's New World
colonies, which
furnished British traders and smugglers
more access to formerly closed Spanish
markets in America.
This agreement also contributed heavily to
the spread of piracy across the Western
Atlantic.
Shipping to the colonies accompanied the
surge of skilled mariners after the war.
Merchant shippers utilized the labor
surplus to push wages down, cut comas to
maximize earnings, and
create unfortunate circumstances aboard
their ships.
Merchant sailors suffered death rates as
high or higher than the slaves being
transported.
Living conditions were so flawed that many
sailors started to choose a freer
lifestyle as pirates.
The expanded volume of shipping traffic
also could support a large body of pirates
preying upon it.
Many pirates had originally been sailors
for privateersmen, the Royal Navy or
merchant seamen during this
time.
Most pirates had experience living on the
ocean and knew how difficult the
circumstances could be.
Sailors for the king usually have very
little to eat while on the sea and end up
starving, sick and dying.
That resulted in some sailors rejecting
the king and becoming pirates instead.
This also permitted pirates to combat the
navy better.
Unlike other seamen, pirates had rigid
rules for how they were treated on the
craft.
Contrary to popular belief, pirate
captains did not have a dictatorship over
the rest of the pirates on their vessels.
Captains had to be voted in and had rigid
regulations to observe.
The captain was not treated better than
the other crewmates and was expected to
treat the gang respectfully.
This was an intended difference to
merchant captains, who usually treated
their crews terribly.
Many pirates had previously been treated
as if they were the ones who were the most
important.
operated on these merchants' vessels and
knew how awful some captains could be.
As a result, vessels often enforced
councils comprising all crew members.
Some councils were employed daily to
create everyday decisions, while others
were utilized as a court system
only when criminal happenings or legal
matters called for it.
Whatever the issue, crew members on pirate
ships usually have as much authority as
the captain outside of battle.
The captain only had complete control in
times of conflict and could be removed
from this position if he showed
coerced in the face of the adversary.
He was also fearless in battle.
The pirates did not want things to end up
the same as on a navy ship.
John Taylor, Olivia Levasseur, Christopher
Condon and Edward England operated from
Madagascar
between 1719 and 1721.
Taylor and Levasseur reaped the most
significant prize in the history of the
Golden Age of Parasy, the
plunder of the Portuguese East in diamond,
Nosso Senhora do Cabo, at Ranean in 1721,
looting diamonds and other treasures.
Condent was also a triumphant pirate, but
England was not.
He was abandoned on Comoros by Taylor and
Levasseur in 1721, and died soon after
that.
Despite the conquest of Tela and
Levasseur, the pirate round fast decreased
again.
The Barbary pirates were pirates and
privateers that worked from the North
African, also known as the Barbary coast,
ports of Algiers, Salé, Morocco, Tunis,
and Tripoli, preying on shipping in the
western Mediterranean
Sea from the ears of the crusades and
ships on their route to Asia around Africa
until the early 19th
century.
They repeatedly assailed the coastal
villages and towns of Italy, Spain and
Mediterranean islands,
and their inhabitants almost completely
abandoned long stretches of the Italian
and Spanish coasts.
Since the 17th century, Barbary pirates
sometimes penetrated the Atlantic and
struck as far north
as Iceland.
According to Robert Davis, between 1
million and 1.25 million Europeans were
arrested by Barbary pirates and sold as
slaves in Northern Africa between the 16th
and 19th centuries.
Barbary pirates prospered in the early
17th century as new sailing rigs by Simon
de Danza
enabled North African raiders, for the
first time, to brave the Atlantic and
Mediterranean waters.
More than 20,000 prisoners were said to be
jailed in Algiers alone.
The rich were permitted to redeem
themselves.
but the poor were sentenced to slavery.
Their masters would, sometimes allow them
to secure freedom by pledging Islam.
Numerous people of good social position
Italians, Germans, English travelers and
Spaniards in the south were
captives for a while.
In 1627 Iceland was subject to raids known
as the Turkish Abductions.
Nur-at-Ris is believed to have taken 400
detainees, 242 of the prisoners, were
later sold into slavery on the Barbary
coast.
The pirates seized only young people and
those in good health.
All those offering opposition were slain,
and the older adults were collected in a
church set on fire.
Among those arrested was Oliver E.
Gilson, who was ransomed the next year
and, upon returning to Iceland, documented
a slave record about
his experience.
Another famous captive from that raid was
Gurdjiluf's Simonar daughter.
The sack of Vestmannaigar is known in the
history of Iceland as Tegcharranid.
While pirates are commonly represented
with eye patches, this myth originated in
19th century novels
and tales of buccaneers, including
compensation for a lost eye.
Few historical pirates wore patches over
their eyes, but some, like the 18th
century Arab pirate Roma
Ibn Jabba al-Jalahima did.
While the golden age of European and
American pirates is typically thought to
have concluded between
1710 and 1730, the prosperity of the
Barbary pirates persisted until the early
19th century.
Unlike the European powers, the young
United States declined to pay tribute to
the Barbary states and
answered with the First Barbary War and
the Second Barbary War against North
Africa.
when the Bargary pirates seized and
enslaved American seafarers.
By the early 18th century, all nations'
tolerance toward privateers was declining.
After the Treaty of Utrecht was signed,
the surplus of trained sailors without a
job was both a godsend and
a scourge for all pirates.
Initially, the abundance of men had
multiplied the number of pirates.
This inevitably led to the raiding of more
vessels, which significantly weakened
trade for all European
nations.
In response, European countries supported
their navies to present merchants with
greater safety and hunt
down pirates.
The surplus of skilled seafarers meant a
large pool could also be drafted into
national navies.
The latter half of 1718, including the
arrival of Governor Woods Rogers in
Nassau, represents a
turning point in the history of piracy in
the New World.
Without a safe base and with increasing
pressure from naval forces, the rovers
lost their momentum.
The appeal of the Spanish treasures had
vanished.
and the hunters slowly became the hunted.
By early 1719, the remaining pirates were
on the run.
Many of them journeyed toward West Africa,
seizing inadequately protected slavers.
The heralded golden age of piracy didn't
last a decade, but tales of
larger-than-life pirates have
endured the test of time.
We've mentioned Blackbeard several times
because he is, without question, one of
the most infamous pirates who ever
lived.
Now, let's dig a bit deeper into the man
and his legacy.
Edward Teach, alternatively known as
Edward Thatch and better known as
Blackbeard, was an English pirate who
worked around the West Indies and the
eastern coast of Britain's North American
territories.
Little is known about his early life, but
he may have been a seafarer on privateer
vessels during Queen Anne's
War before he decided on the Bahamian
island of New Providence.
a base for Captain Benjamin Hornigold,
whose crew teach Halide with around 1716.
Hornigold placed him in power of a sloop
that he had seized, and the two took part
in multiple acts of
piracy.
Their fleet was increased by the addition
of two more ships, one of which was
controlled by Steed Bonnet, but
Hornigold withdrew from piracy toward the
end of 1717, taking two boats with him.
Teach seized a French slave ship, Le
Concorde, renamed her Queen Anne's
Revenge, provided her with
40 guns and crewed her with over 300 men.
He became a famed pirate.
His nickname derived from his fearsome
appearance and thick black beard.
He was documented to have tied lit fuses
under his hat to scare his enemies.
He joined with pirates and secured the
port of Charlestown, South Carolina.
ransoming the harbour's residents.
He then ran Queen Anne's Revenge aground
on a sandbar near Beaufort, North
Carolina.
He parted company with Steed Bonnet and
settled in Bath, North Carolina, also
known as Bathtown, where
he obtained a royal pardon.
However, he was soon back at sea, where he
drew the attention of Alexander Spotswood,
the governor of Virginia.
Spotswood organised a party of sailors and
soldiers to capture him.
On November 22nd, 1718, after a fierce
battle, Teach and several of
his crew were slain by a small force of
sailors led by Lieutenant Robert Maynard.
He was allegedly stabbed 20 times and shot
five times before death.
Teach was a savvy and calculating leader
who disregarded violence, relying instead
on his fearsome image to
evoke the reaction he wanted from those he
robbed.
He was glorified after his death and
became the inspiration for an archetypal
pirate in works of fiction
across many genres.
Since the end of the golden age of piracy,
Teach and his exploits have become the
stuff of legend,
inspiring books, films and even amusement
park rides.
Much of what is known about him can be
sourced from Charles Johnson's A General
History of the Robberies and Murders of
the Most Notorious Pirates.
published in Britain in 1724, a recognized
authority on the pirates of his time.
Johnson's descriptions of such figures, as
Anne Bonny and Mary Read were for years,
required reading for those
interested in the subject.
His stories fascinated readers, and the
second edition was quickly published.
However, author Angus Constam suspects
that Johnson's entry on Blackbeard was
colored a little to make a more
sensational story.
Her general history, though, is generally
considered to be a reliable source.
Johnson may have been an assumed alias.
As Johnson's accounts have been
corroborated in personal and official
dispatches, Lee believes that whoever he
was,
he had some access to official
correspondence.
Constam speculates further, suggesting
that Johnson may have been the English
playwright Charles Johnson, the British
publisher Charles Rivington, or the writer
Daniel Defoe.
In his 1951 work, The Great Days of
Parasy, author George Woodbury wrote that
Johnson is
obviously a pseudonym, continuing, one
cannot help suspecting that he may have
been a pirate himself.
Teach used black flags with death heads
and bloody flags to intimidate his
enemies.
Nevertheless, the flag, commonly
attributed to Blackbeard, depicting a
horned skeleton spearing a heart while
toasting the devil, was probably never
actually used by him.
Despite his infamy, Teach was not the most
successful of pirates.
Henry Every retired a rich man, and
Bartholomew Roberts took an estimated five
times the amount
Teach stole.
Treasure hunters have long busied
themselves searching for any trace of his
rumored hoard of gold and silver, but
nothing in the numerous sites explored
along the east coast of the US has ever
been connected to him.
Some tales suggest that pirates often
killed a prisoner on the spot where they
buried their loot, and Teach is no
exception in these stories, but that no
finds of counter-light is not exceptional.
The buried pirate treasure is often
considered a modern myth for which almost
no supporting evidence exists.
The available records include nothing to
suggest that the burial of treasure was a
common practice, except in the
imaginations of the writers of fictional
accounts such as Treasure Island.
Such holds would necessitate a wealthy
owner, and their supposed existence
ignores the command structure of a
pirate vessel, in which the crew served
for a share of the profit.
The only pirate ever known to bury
treasure was William Kidd.
The only treasure so far recovered from
Teach's exploits is that taken from the
wreckage of what is presumed to be
the Queen Anne's Revenge, which was found
in 1996.
As of 2009, more than 250,000 artifacts
have been recovered.
A selection is on public display at the
North Carolina Maritime Museum.
Various superstitious tales exist of
Teach's ghost.
Unexplained lights at sea are often
referred to as Teach's light.
Some recitals claim that the notorious
pirate now roams the afterlife, searching
for his head for fear that his
friends and the devil will not recognize
him.
A North Carolinian tale holds that Teach's
skull was used as the basis for a silver
drinking chalice.
A local judge even claimed to have drunk
from it one night in the 1930s.
The name of Blackbeard has been attached
to many local attractions, such as
Charleston's Blackbeard's Cove.
His name and persona have also featured
heavily in literature.
He is the main subject of Matilda Douglas'
fictional 1835 work Blackbeard, a page
from the colonial history of Philadelphia,
film renditions of his life, include
Blackbeard the Pirates starring
West Country native Robert Newton, whose
exaggerated West Country accent is
credited with popularizing the
stereotypical pirate voice, Blackbeard's
ghost, Blackbeard, Terror at Sea, and the
Hallmark Channel miniseries Blackbeard.
Parallels have also been drawn between
Johnson's Blackbeard and the character of
Captain Jack Sparrow in the adventure
film Pirates of the Caribbean.
The Curse of the Black Pearl.
Speaking of Disney's Pirates of the
Caribbean, no tales of piracy could be
told without mentioning the
blockbuster franchise.
Pirates of the Caribbean is an American
fantasy swashbuckler movie series produced
by Jerry Bruckheimer
and based on Walt Disney's theme park ride
of the same name.
The film series acts as an essential part
of the eponymous pirate's universe.
Directors of the series include Gore
Verbinski, who directed films 1 through 3,
Rob Marshall, who
directed part 4, Joachim Ronning and Espen
Sandberg, who co-directed part 5.
Ted Elliott primarily wrote the series,
and Terry Rossio co-wrote parts 1 through
4.
Other writers include Stuart Beattie in
part 1, Jay Walpert in part 1, Jeff
Nathanson in part 5,
and Craig Mazin in part 6.
The tales track the adventures of Captain
Jack Sparrow, portrayed by Johnny Depp,
Will Turner, portrayed by
Orlando Bloom, and Elizabeth Swann,
portrayed by Keira Knightley.
Characters such as Hector Barbosa,
portrayed by Geoffrey Rush, and Joshimi
Gibbs, portrayed by Kevin
McNally, follow Jack, Will and Elizabeth
throughout the films.
Other main characters include James
Norrington, portrayed by Jack Davenport,
Davy Jones, portrayed by Bill
Nighy and Tia Dalma, portrayed by Naomi
Harris.
The fourth film features Blackbeard,
played by Ian McShane and Angelica
Penelope Cruz.
The fifth film features Armando Salazar,
played by Gavia Bardem, Henry Turner.
played by Brenton Thwaites, and Carina
Smith, played by Kea Scodelario.
The movies take place in a fictionalised
interpretation of the golden age of piracy
and are set mainly in the
Caribbean.
The movie franchise started in 2003 with
Pirates of the Caribbean, The Curse of the
Black Pearl,
which had a favourable reception from film
critics and audiences.
It grossed $654 million worldwide.
After the first film sensation, Walt
Disney Pictures disclosed that a film
franchise was in the works.
The second film, subtitled Dead Man's
Chest, came out in 2006 and shattered
financial
records worldwide on the day of its
premiere.
Dead Man's Chest became the top grossing
movie of 2006 with nearly $1.1
billion at the worldwide box office.
The third film in the franchise, subtitled
At World's End, followed in 2007, earning
$960 million.
Disney released a fourth film, subtitled
On Stranger Tides, in 2011 in conventional
2D,
digital 3D, and IMAX 3D.
On Stranger Tides also took in more than
$1 billion at the box office.
becoming the second film in the franchise
and only the eighth film in history to do
this at the time of release.
A fifth film, subtitled Dead Men Tell No
Tales, was released in 2017.
The Pirates of the Caribbean franchise has
grossed over $4.5 billion globally.
It is the 14th highest-grossing movie
series of all time and is the first film
franchise to produce two
or more movies you that took in over $1
billion.
So much money, so much gold, so much
treasure.
But how would you go about actually
finding real treasures?
You'd need to become a treasure hunter, of
course.
What's that, you ask?
Let's find out.
Treasure hunting is the physical
investigation of the whereabouts of
treasure.
For example, treasure hunters try to find
underwater wreckages and rescue market
value antiques and
relics.
The demand for antiquities typically
motivates this industry.
The procedure of treasure hunting can be
contentious, as areas such as submerged
shipwrecks or cultural regions
could be protected by national or
international regulations interested in
marine salvage, property ownership,
commercial diving regulations, sovereign
or state vessels, trade controls,
protection of cultural heritage.
Treasure hunting can also refer to
geocaching, a sport in which players use
GPS units to
locate hidden stockpiles of trinkets,
toys, or other treasure hunting games.
What is the history of treasure hunting?
In 1643, Massachusetts treasure hunter Sir
William Phipps recovered a sunken Spanish
treasure
ship that had been shipwrecked on the
Ambrosia Bank in 1599.
The entire worth of the treasures rescued
came in at 205,536 pounds.
The Nuestra Señora de Tocha departed
Havana bound for Spain in 1622 before
shipwrecking.
American treasure hunter Mel Fisher and
his crew spent 16 years scouring for the
Nuestra Señora de
Tocha's remains.
Three silver bars were located in 1973.
Five bronze cannons were discovered in
1975, and a wooden hull weighted down by
ballast rocks,
iron cannonballs, and antiques in 1980 of
17th century Spain was uncovered,
documenting
the site of the shipwreck.
The SS Central America crashed after
sailing into a hurricane off the Carolina
coast in 1857.
In 1987, Thomas G.
Thompson located the ship's wreck, A.
ROUV surfaced with over $40 million in
gold from the shipwreck.
In 1782, the EIC East in Diamond Rovina
sank off the Cape Colony while bearing a
load of
2,000 silver ingots, several jewels of
unknown value, and 720 gold ingots.
In 1952, a British crew retrieved nearly
£1 million worth of the
£5.3 million in freight, concealed in
Brazil to evade being taxed by the British
government.
The SS Laurentic on a journey from
Liverpool to Halifax in 1917, crashed into
a
mine and sunk with a gold payload worth 5
million pounds.
The British Admiralty selected Butenant
Commander G.C.C.
Damant to recover the ship.
Damant, assisted by John Haldane, found
the reason and prevention of decompression
sickness, the bends,
permitting them to make deeper plunges.
Over several seasons, All but 25 gold bars
were retrieved by Damant and his crew.
In 2002, the Odyssey Marine Exploration
joined into an agreement with the British
government to
find HMS Sussex, which harboured 10 tonnes
of gold coins on board.
The ship was founded in 1694 off the coast
of Gibraltar.
In 2009, Englishman Terry Herbert found a
cache of Anglo-Saxon gold and silver
metalwork you called the Staffordshire
Hoard.
The same year, Scotsman David Booth
discovered four gold torques from the 1st
century BC in
Stirling, Scotland.
Since the late 1990s, reacting against
increasingly vigorous endeavours by the
international community
to stop the collapse of the world's
immersed cultural heritage,
treasure-hunting businesses began
employing
archaeologists and marketing directors
making public announcements about their
good intentions.
Even where fine-grade archaeological
analysis is carried out by archaeologists
working with treasure hunters,
worries persist that treasure hunting, by
definition, ignores the principle that the
protection of cultural heritage
should continually be assessed first, and
that the selling of recovered antiques
splits up the group of cultural heritage
material, resulting in a loss of the
possibility to examine the whole
situation.
The counter-argument is that experienced
treasure hunters have the means to finance
archaeological research of areas
that would otherwise be unregistered and
be subject to demolition by looting all
natural forces.
The early stages of the evolution of
archaeology contained a vital element of
treasure hunting, Heinrich
Schliemann's excavations of Troy, and
later at Mycenae each turned up
significant discoveries of golden
antiques.
Early work in Egyptology also had a
similar rationale.
Contemporary non-expert treasure hunters
use relatively cheap methyl detectors to
locate finds at terrestrial
sites.
Aquatic archaeologist and sometime
treasure hunter Peter Throckmorton, in a
paper he authored in
1969 as part of a historical archaeology
forum on E.
Lee Spence's salvage of a Civil War
blockade runner, addresses the query of
whether treasure hunting and
archaeology clash, said, The foregoing
discussion may seem like an attack on Mr.
Spence.
I do not mean this to be so.
A whole new branch of archaeology, that of
Mycenaean studies, was founded by Heinrich
Schlemmann, who also
had the courage to remember his dreams.
It is right to dream, and it would be the
worst kind of mistake on the part of the
state to discourage the big
dreams of men like Mr.
Spence, and to let a project requiring
that sort of enterprise fall into the
hands of what Mr.
Spence's friend terms some bloody
historical society, which might lay the
dead hand of unimaginative and
stereotyped thinking on Mr.
Spence's courage and ability.
In 1972, Spence and Throckmorton Alongside
three other men were awarded the degree of
Doctor of Marine Histories by the College
of Marine Arts on July 16th 1972, becoming
the
first people in the world to be granted a
doctorate for work in marine archaeology.
More recently, numerous treasure hunters
have commenced working underwater, where
current technology allows
entry to wrecks possessing previously
unreachable valuables.
each new generation of technology has made
other wrecks more accessible, starting
with the diving suit, moving
on through scuba, and finally to ROVs.
Many of these wrecks have resulted in the
treasure salvage of many intriguing relics
from Spanish treasure feats
and numerous others.
Equipment.
Rubberized suits, weighted straps and
shoes, and helmets are used for deep sea
diving.
Diving bells, open helmets, and
atmospheric diving suits were employed.
Deep sea exploration today is achieved
utilizing self-contained underwater
breathing apparatus SCUBA.
Uncrewed submersible vehicles, remote
operating vehicles, ROVs and exposure
suits,
sound navigation and ranging sonar and
magnetometers are utilized to find
treasure.
And tools, probes, screens, containers,
shovels, metal detectors, and sifters are
useful for treasure
hunting on land.
The Evinrude Aquanaut is a mobile floating
diving unit that provides air directly to
the divers without the
demand for tanks on the divers.
In diving, masks permit better vision,
fins improve swimming speeds, safety vests
offer
life-saving assistance, divers' flags
alert others of a diver's surroundings,
wetsuits save body heat
and also deliver skin protection.
Weight belts counteract the buoyancy of
rubber suits, knives are helpful as a
tool, tanks provide air, and
snorkels save energy.
Legality In 1906, the Secretaries of the
Interior of Agriculture and War wrote an
Act
to Maintain American Antiquities.
This Act states that each of the Interior
would have detailed authority over other
artifacts or sites based on
their division.
These relics and sites are as follows.
Historic landmarks.
Historic monuments.
Objects of antiquity.
Objects of scientific and historical
value.
The Secretary of Agriculture has
jurisdiction over artifacts and monuments
found within the outer limits of
forest reserves.
The Secretary of War for any ground in or
near a military reserve.
The respective secretary will manage the
lands that the US government governs.
Permits will not be given to those trying
to move or take any monument or artefact
that can be maintained in its
original place and stay as an ancient
monument.
A permit will not be given to someone
whose eyes are bigger than their stomach.
In other words, that permit will not be
provided to those attempting to explore a
vast region with scant help,
and the job seems not to be accomplished
within the time limits specified by a
certain someone.
Each permit will be given by the
respective secretaries that have
jurisdiction over those particular sites.
Also, including the license just noted
above, You also need the subsequent
requirements.
The name of the institution making the
request.
How much time will it take?
The date, the person in charge of the
project.
What type of project is it going to be
excavating, gathering or examining?
The museum where the artefact will be
shown and preserved.
Each permit will only be given for three
years or less.
An extension can be provided if progress
is indicated.
Permits will not be in effect if work does
not start within six months of being
granted the permit.
The United States Federal Abandoned
Shipwrecks Act, which maintains the
Federal Government's ownership of
abandoned
United States water shipwrecks, was
executed in 1988.
Any wreckage entrenched in submerged lands
and or coralline formations safeguarded by
a state on a
state's submerged grounds is the
government's property.
The Abandoned Shipwrecks Act then assigns
ownership to the relevant state
government.
The Supreme Court upheld the Abandoned
Shipwrecks Act constitutionality in 1998.
In the US, the finder of a ship not
deserted could seek a salvage award.
England, Wales and Northern Ireland claim
gold and silver discoveries that are more
than 300 years old for
the Crown via the Treasure Act of 1996.
Any uncovered treasure in these nations
must be declared within 14 days of
discovery.
The United States grants ownership to the
landowner.
It can be deemed a federal offense if
fines happen on federal land.
Most of the United States prosecutes the
unearthing of burial grounds.
Criticism.
A growing number of nations rebuke
treasure hunting, and the UNESCO issued a
Charter for Safeguarding Underwater
Cultural Heritage.
in 2001, the UNESCO Convention on the
Protection of the Underwater Cultural
Heritage.
This convention is a legal instrument
helping state parties to improve the
protection of their underwater cultural
heritage.
In 2013, the National Geographic Channel
began a controversy with its reality
program Diggers,
professional archaeologists from the
Society for Historical Archaeology, the
most influential scholarly group.
Interested in the archaeology of the
modern world AD 1400 to the present,
Roundley condemned the
network for promoting the theft of
cultural materials on public and private
land.
Notable treasure hunters Martin Bale
located the shipwreck of R.M.S.
Republic in 1981.
Brent Brisbane, founder of 1715 Fleet,
Queen's Jewels, Hell L.C.
Owners of the identified remains of the
1715 plate fleet.
John Chatterton, discoverer of the pirate
ship of Joseph Bandsister Golden Fleece.
Mel Fisher, discoverer of the Spanish
gullion Nuestra Senora de Tocha.
Cork Graham, war correspondent, author.
Mike Hatcher, discoverer of the Nanking
cargo.
Robert F.
Marks, underwater archaeologist, author.
John Matera, author.
and discoverer of the pirate ship of
Joseph Bandsister Golden Fleece.
Juan Ponce de León searched the New World
for gold and the Fountain of Youth.
E.
Lee Spence, pioneer underwater
archaeologist, discoverer of the Hunley SS
Ozama,
SS Georgiana, etc.
Philip Masters discovered Blackbeard's
flagship, the Queen Anne's Revenge, in
1996.
Notable Treasure Hunting Companies
Columbus America Discovery Group located
and salvaged treasure
from the 1857 shipwreck of the SS Central
America.
Using research by Dr.
E.
Lee Spence, Intersol, Inc., while working
under permit from the state of North
Carolina,
discovered the pirate Blackbeard's
flagship, the Queen Anne's Revenge, on
November 21,
1996.
Lords of Fortune LLC is engaged in the
recovery of the SARS treasure from the
famous treasure
shipwreck RMS Republic.
Odyssey Marine Exploration located and
salvaged treasure from 1865 shipwrecks of
the
S.S.
Republic, using research by Dr.
E.
Lee Spence.
Shipwrecks, Inc., chartered in 1967 by Dr.
E.
Lee Spence, received first salvage license
issued in South Carolina for work on
C.S.S.
Georgiana.
Treasure Salvers, Inc., founded by Mel
Fisher, located I'm David.
the Nuestra Señora de Toca wreck and its
mother load of silver, gold and emeralds
in July
1985.
And there you have it, everything there is
to know about pirates and treasure
hunting.
Join us for another episode of DOP TV's
monster horror documentary series soon.